<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Inferno</title>
            <author>Dante Alighieri</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>translated by</resp>
               <name>Henry Wadsworth Longfellow</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Project Gutenberg</publisher>
            <availability>
               <p>https://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/1004/pg1004-images.html#CantoI.I</p>
            </availability>
            <date type="release">August 1, 1997</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Translation of the Inferno, by Dante Alighieri</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This encoded file was created by members of the Linked Editing Academic Framework
               (LEAF) team and made available for a LEAF / LEAF-Writer workshop. This file is not
               meant for use or publication outside of the workshop environment.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English language translation</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb facs="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/38/Inferno_Canto_4_four_bards.jpg"/>
            <head>The Inferno: Canto IV</head>
            <byline>Dante Alighieri</byline>
            <lg n="1">
               <l n="1">Broke the deep lethargy within my head</l>
               <l n="2">A heavy thunder, so that I upstarted,</l>
               <l n="3">Like to a person who by force is wakened;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="2">
               <l n="4">And round about I moved my rested eyes,</l>
               <l n="5">Uprisen erect, and steadfastly I gazed,</l>
               <l n="6">To recognise the place wherein I was.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="3">
               <l n="7">True is it, that upon the verge I found me</l>
               <l n="8">Of the abysmal valley dolorous,</l>
               <l n="9">That gathers thunder of infinite ululations.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="4">
               <l n="10">Obscure, profound it was, and nebulous,</l>
               <l n="11">So that by fixing on its depths my sight</l>
               <l n="12">Nothing whatever I discerned therein.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="5">
               <l n="13">“Let us descend now into the blind world,”</l>
               <l n="14">Began the Poet, pallid utterly;</l>
               <l n="15">“I will be first, and thou shalt second be.”</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="6">
               <l n="16">And I, who of his colour was aware,</l>
               <l n="17">Said: “How shall I come, if thou art afraid,</l>
               <l n="18">Who’rt wont to be a comfort to my fears?”</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="7">
               <l n="19">And he to me: “The anguish of the people</l>
               <l n="20">Who are below here in my face depicts</l>
               <l n="21">That pity which for terror thou hast taken.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="8">
               <l n="22">Let us go on, for the long way impels us.”</l>
               <l n="23">Thus he went in, and thus he made me enter</l>
               <l n="24">The foremost circle that surrounds the abyss.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="9">
               <l n="25">There, as it seemed to me from listening,</l>
               <l n="26">Were lamentations none, but only sighs,</l>
               <l n="27">That tremble made the everlasting air.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="10">
               <l n="28">And this arose from sorrow without torment,</l>
               <l n="29">Which the crowds had, that many were and great,</l>
               <l n="30">Of infants and of women and of men.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="11">
               <l n="31">To me the Master good: “Thou dost not ask</l>
               <l n="32">What spirits these, which thou beholdest, are?</l>
               <l n="33">Now will I have thee know, ere thou go farther,</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="12">
               <l n="34">That they sinned not; and if they merit had,</l>
               <l n="35">’Tis not enough, because they had not baptism</l>
               <l n="36">Which is the portal of the Faith thou holdest;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="13">
               <l n="37">And if they were before Christianity,</l>
               <l n="38">In the right manner they adored not God;</l>
               <l n="39">And among such as these am I myself.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="14">
               <l n="40">For such defects, and not for other guilt,</l>
               <l n="41">Lost are we and are only so far punished,</l>
               <l n="42">That without hope we live on in desire.”</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="15">
               <l n="43">Great grief seized on my heart when this I heard,</l>
               <l n="44">Because some people of much worthiness</l>
               <l n="45">I knew, who in that Limbo were suspended.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="16">
               <l n="46">“Tell me, my Master, tell me, thou my Lord,”</l>
               <l n="47">Began I, with desire of being certain</l>
               <l n="48">Of that Faith which o’ercometh every error,</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="17">
               <l n="49">“Came any one by his own merit hence,</l>
               <l n="50">Or by another’s, who was blessed thereafter?”</l>
               <l n="51">And he, who understood my covert speech,</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="18">
               <l n="52">Replied: “I was a novice in this state,</l>
               <l n="53">When I saw hither come a Mighty One,</l>
               <l n="54">With sign of victory incoronate.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="19">
               <l n="55">Hence he drew forth the shade of the First Parent,</l>
               <l n="56">And that of his son Abel, and of Noah,</l>
               <l n="57">Of Moses the lawgiver, and the obedient</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="20">
               <l n="58">Abraham, patriarch, and David, king,</l>
               <l n="59">Israel with his father and his children,</l>
               <l n="60">And Rachel, for whose sake he did so much,</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="21">
               <l n="61">And others many, and he made them blessed;</l>
               <l n="62">And thou must know, that earlier than these</l>
               <l n="63">Never were any human spirits saved.”</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="22">
               <l n="64">We ceased not to advance because he spake,</l>
               <l n="65">But still were passing onward through the forest,</l>
               <l n="66">The forest, say I, of thick-crowded ghosts.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="23">
               <l n="67">Not very far as yet our way had gone</l>
               <l n="68">This side the summit, when I saw a fire</l>
               <l n="69">That overcame a hemisphere of darkness.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="24">
               <l n="70">We were a little distant from it still,</l>
               <l n="71">But not so far that I in part discerned not</l>
               <l n="72">That honourable people held that place.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="25">
               <l n="73">“O thou who honourest every art and science,</l>
               <l n="74">Who may these be, which such great honour have,</l>
               <l n="75">That from the fashion of the rest it parts them?”</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="26">
               <l n="76">And he to me: “The honourable name,</l>
               <l n="77">That sounds of them above there in thy life,</l>
               <l n="78">Wins grace in Heaven, that so advances them.”</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="27">
               <l n="79">In the mean time a voice was heard by me:</l>
               <l n="80">“All honour be to the pre-eminent Poet;</l>
               <l n="81">His shade returns again, that was departed.”</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="28">
               <l n="82">After the voice had ceased and quiet was,</l>
               <l n="83">Four mighty shades I saw approaching us;</l>
               <l n="84">Semblance had they nor sorrowful nor glad.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="29">
               <l n="85">To say to me began my gracious Master:</l>
               <l n="86">“Him with that falchion in his hand behold,</l>
               <l n="87">Who comes before the three, even as their lord.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="30">
               <l n="88">That one is Homer, Poet sovereign;</l>
               <l n="89">He who comes next is Horace, the satirist;</l>
               <l n="90">The third is Ovid, and the last is Lucan.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="31">
               <l n="91">Because to each of these with me applies</l>
               <l n="92">The name that solitary voice proclaimed,</l>
               <l n="93">They do me honour, and in that do well.”</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="32">
               <l n="94">Thus I beheld assemble the fair school</l>
               <l n="95">Of that lord of the song pre-eminent,</l>
               <l n="96">Who o’er the others like an eagle soars.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="33">
               <l n="97">When they together had discoursed somewhat,</l>
               <l n="98">They turned to me with signs of salutation,</l>
               <l n="99">And on beholding this, my Master smiled;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="34">
               <l n="100">And more of honour still, much more, they did me,</l>
               <l n="101">In that they made me one of their own band;</l>
               <l n="102">So that the sixth was I, ’mid so much wit.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="35">
               <l n="103">Thus we went on as far as to the light,</l>
               <l n="104">Things saying ’tis becoming to keep silent,</l>
               <l n="105">As was the saying of them where I was.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="36">
               <l n="106">We came unto a noble castle’s foot,</l>
               <l n="107">Seven times encompassed with lofty walls,</l>
               <l n="108">Defended round by a fair rivulet;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="37">
               <l n="109">This we passed over even as firm ground;</l>
               <l n="110">Through portals seven I entered with these Sages;</l>
               <l n="111">We came into a meadow of fresh verdure.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="38">
               <l n="112">People were there with solemn eyes and slow,</l>
               <l n="113">Of great authority in their countenance;</l>
               <l n="114">They spake but seldom, and with gentle voices.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="39">
               <l n="115">Thus we withdrew ourselves upon one side</l>
               <l n="116">Into an opening luminous and lofty,</l>
               <l n="117">So that they all of them were visible.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="40">
               <l n="118">There opposite, upon the green enamel,</l>
               <l n="119">Were pointed out to me the mighty spirits,</l>
               <l n="120">Whom to have seen I feel myself exalted.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="41">
               <l n="121">I saw Electra with companions many,</l>
               <l n="122">’Mongst whom I knew both Hector and Aeneas,</l>
               <l n="123">Caesar in armour with gerfalcon eyes;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="42">
               <l n="124">I saw Camilla and Penthesilea</l>
               <l n="125">On the other side, and saw the King Latinus,</l>
               <l n="126">Who with Lavinia his daughter sat;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="43">
               <l n="127">I saw that Brutus who drove Tarquin forth,</l>
               <l n="128">Lucretia, Julia, Marcia, and Cornelia,</l>
               <l n="129">And saw alone, apart, the Saladin.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="44">
               <l n="130">When I had lifted up my brows a little,</l>
               <l n="131">The Master I beheld of those who know,</l>
               <l n="132">Sit with his philosophic family.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="45">
               <l n="133">All gaze upon him, and all do him honour.</l>
               <l n="134">There I beheld both Socrates and Plato,</l>
               <l n="135">Who nearer him before the others stand;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="46">
               <l n="136">Democritus, who puts the world on chance,</l>
               <l n="137">Diogenes, Anaxagoras, and Thales,</l>
               <l n="138">Zeno, Empedocles, and Heraclitus;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="47">
               <l n="139">Of qualities I saw the good collector,</l>
               <l n="140">Hight Dioscorides; and Orpheus saw I,</l>
               <l n="141">Tully and Livy, and moral Seneca,</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="48">
               <l n="142">Euclid, geometrician, and Ptolemy,</l>
               <l n="143">Galen, Hippocrates, and Avicenna,</l>
               <l n="144">Averroes, who the great Comment made.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="49">
               <l n="145">I cannot all of them pourtray in full,</l>
               <l n="146">Because so drives me onward the long theme,</l>
               <l n="147">That many times the word comes short of fact.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="50">
               <l n="148">The sixfold company in two divides;</l>
               <l n="149">Another way my sapient Guide conducts me</l>
               <l n="150">Forth from the quiet to the air that trembles;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg n="51">
               <l n="151">And to a place I come where nothing shines.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
